<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>CRAFTING LIVES IN BRUSSELS MAKING AND MOBILITY ON THE MARGINS</title>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <p>Testing.</p>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="level1" xml:id="introduction">
  <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
  
    <p>WHERE WE GET TO KNOW BRUSSELS, <hi rendition="simple:italic">THE
    MOST BEAUTIFUL OF ALL THE UGLY CITIES,</hi> WITH ITS RICH AND
    SEPARATED LAYERS, CONTRASTING IDENTITIES AND MULTIPLE STORIES; WHERE
    WE WILL QUESTION ITS PORTRAYAL AS A GLOBAL CITY AND EXPERIENCE ITS
    BOUNDARIES, EXCLUSIONS AND OBSTACLES; WHERE WE WILL DISCOVER THE
    GROUND THROUGH STORIES AND DRINK PEPPERMINT TEA WITH YUNUS, CISE AND
    HAMUDA, SITUATE THIS STORY AND ITS CHALLENGES WITHIN THE LARGER
    FRAMEWORK OF MOBILITY AND MARGINS AND PROVIDE WHAT ELSE IS NEEDED TO
    CONTINUE WITH THIS TALE.</p>
    <p>The clattering of the heavily filled shopping trolleys on the
    concrete cobbles mingles with the competing announcements of the
    market sellers. With a repetitive ‘Nothing is expensive, everything
    cheap, nothing explosive!’<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="1"><p><!--1--> Originally in French,
    translation by the author. French was my main language in fieldwork,
    Tunisian Arabic was used on a few occasions. Considering
    translation, see Chapter 2.</p></note>
    one of them advertises his colourful products. People living in
    Molenbeek, Brussels, are well aware of their persisting
    international reputation. ‘Europe’s jihadi central’ (Traynor 2015),
    ‘The Islamic State of Molenbeek’ (Cohen 2016) and ‘Crucible of
    Terror’ (Jones 2015) are only some of the many depictions that were
    decorating front pages all across local and international
    newspapers. Here at the weekly Thursday market the collected
    publications are for sale alongside fresh fruits and vegetables, the
    newest, most fashionable headscarves, praying rugs and whatever one
    would need to save space in the ever-so-small apartments in the
    area. It is a quite unusually sunny day in Brussels. Although, while
    finding my way through the much too crowded narrow market streets, I
    am thinking that my notebook is filled with the remark of ‘unusually
    bright days’. My sometimes messy and too quickly written thoughts
    are often accompanied by observations of current weather conditions.
    Unusual sunny days that I spent outside, wandering around, meeting
    people, usually alternate with descriptions of the many more grey
    days when I preferred to stay inside the wood-studio, reminiscing
    about the famous blue sky in Tunisia with my colleague and teacher
    Hamuda. While walking, I remember Ingold’s observation that given
    the centrality of weather to life and experience, and its influence
    on moods and motivations, its absence from anthropological accounts
    of human ways of being and knowing is quite remarkable (2010a:
    132).</p>
      <p><media xml:id="v:1-2" url="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/1.-Molenbeeks-fame.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"></media></p>
      <p>[…] </p>
  </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>