<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>CRAFTING LIVES IN BRUSSELS MAKING AND MOBILITY ON THE MARGINS</title>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <p>Testing.</p>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="level1" xml:id="introduction">
  <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
  
    <p>WHERE WE GET TO KNOW BRUSSELS, <hi rendition="simple:italic">THE
    MOST BEAUTIFUL OF ALL THE UGLY CITIES,</hi> WITH ITS RICH AND
    SEPARATED LAYERS, CONTRASTING IDENTITIES AND MULTIPLE STORIES; WHERE
    WE WILL QUESTION ITS PORTRAYAL AS A GLOBAL CITY AND EXPERIENCE ITS
    BOUNDARIES, EXCLUSIONS AND OBSTACLES; WHERE WE WILL DISCOVER THE
    GROUND THROUGH STORIES AND DRINK PEPPERMINT TEA WITH YUNUS, CISE AND
    HAMUDA, SITUATE THIS STORY AND ITS CHALLENGES WITHIN THE LARGER
    FRAMEWORK OF MOBILITY AND MARGINS AND PROVIDE WHAT ELSE IS NEEDED TO
    CONTINUE WITH THIS TALE.</p>
    <p>The clattering of the heavily filled shopping trolleys on the
    concrete cobbles mingles with the competing announcements of the
    market sellers. With a repetitive ‘Nothing is expensive, everything
    cheap, nothing explosive!’<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="1"><p><!--1--> Originally in French,
    translation by the author. French was my main language in fieldwork,
    Tunisian Arabic was used on a few occasions. Considering
    translation, see Chapter 2.</p></note>
    one of them advertises his colourful products. People living in
    Molenbeek, Brussels, are well aware of their persisting
    international reputation. ‘Europe’s jihadi central’ (Traynor 2015),
    ‘The Islamic State of Molenbeek’ (Cohen 2016) and ‘Crucible of
    Terror’ (Jones 2015) are only some of the many depictions that were
    decorating front pages all across local and international
    newspapers. Here at the weekly Thursday market the collected
    publications are for sale alongside fresh fruits and vegetables, the
    newest, most fashionable headscarves, praying rugs and whatever one
    would need to save space in the ever-so-small apartments in the
    area. It is a quite unusually sunny day in Brussels. Although, while
    finding my way through the much too crowded narrow market streets, I
    am thinking that my notebook is filled with the remark of ‘unusually
    bright days’. My sometimes messy and too quickly written thoughts
    are often accompanied by observations of current weather conditions.
    Unusual sunny days that I spent outside, wandering around, meeting
    people, usually alternate with descriptions of the many more grey
    days when I preferred to stay inside the wood-studio, reminiscing
    about the famous blue sky in Tunisia with my colleague and teacher
    Hamuda. While walking, I remember Ingold’s observation that given
    the centrality of weather to life and experience, and its influence
    on moods and motivations, its absence from anthropological accounts
    of human ways of being and knowing is quite remarkable (2010a:
    132).</p>
      <p><media url="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/1.-Molenbeeks-fame.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"></media></p>
      
      <!--<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="2"><p><!-\-2-\-> See:
    <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/1-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/1-2/</ref></p></note>-->
    <p><figure>
      <graphic url="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/origami_black_hole_2x.png" height="400px"/>
    </figure></p>
    <p>I returned to Molenbeek’s market in winter 2015 for the first
    time after the series of attacks in Brussels’s ‘bigger sister’,
    Paris, the previous month, in order to meet my research participants
    Hamuda Djerbi and Cise Ibrahima in our usual
    lunch-place.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="3"><p><!--3--> For a brief summary of
    the events, see Chapter 6.</p></note> Since the end
    of our shared year in a carpentry studio, we had been in touch via
    social media frequently. They had kept me updated on their everyday
    working life, on the ambience of the
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">quartier</hi> during the lock-down, on
    their failed attempts to meet each other. Now that I was gone, after I had left the ‘field’, nobody
    had resumed the initiative and organisation to meet up, as they
    wrote me with a slightly accusatory undertone via Facebook.
    ‘Anthropologists go away: the people you work with know you are
    going to go away. They are stuck there’, writes Hobart (1996: 15),
    describing the process of distancing ourselves, geographically or
    not, from the people and places that guide our writing.</p>
    <p>In the midst of the market’s hustle and bustle of selling,
    buying, chatting and surging, I stumble into
    Yunus<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="4"><p><!--4--> Name changed by the
    author.</p></note> who is spending his
    lunch break on the terrace of the restaurant ‘Al Andalus’. He and
    Hedi, the owner of the area’s popular meeting point known in the
    neighbourhood for its delicious as well as surprisingly affordable
    food, welcome me warm-heartedly. ‘You are still coming here? You are
    not afraid of entering Molenbeek? Then maybe you could bring along
    some of your blond friends next time so they see that one can
    continue eating good food safely here’, Hedi jokes, while serving me
    my favourite soup. After more than a year he knows my lunch
    preferences only too well. It was Yunus who introduced me to the ‘Al
    Andalus’ at the beginning of our training in September 2014. ‘You
    cannot leave your scooter like this on the street! Don’t you know
    that you are surrounded by criminals here?’ was the first sentence
    he said to me with a big grin in his boyish face – already back then
    making fun of Molenbeek’s fame. The national and then international
    reputation of Molenbeek has played a prominent role during my time
    in Brussels, working, walking and talking with Hamuda, Cise, Yunus
    and others, or sometimes just alone to get a fresh breath of air
    after a loud and hectic morning in the carpentry studio. The events
    that occurred during my year at the carpentry centre started with
    the ‘Charlie Hebdo shooting’ in January 2015 in Paris, and were
    followed by incidents in Brussels, Barcelona, London and other
    cities throughout Europe. The name Molenbeek continued to pop up in
    international news ever since when talking about Europe’s
    marginalised ‘ghettos’. Here, the events were not only visible
    ‘outside on the streets’ due to the constant military and police
    presence in the entire city, but were also a recurring topic of
    discussion within the training-centre.</p>
    <p>Yunus took part in this training to use one of his last chances
    to obtain a professional degree despite having dropped out from
    school. He was the youngest of the crowd, 19, clumsy and skinny, one
    of the many sons of Moroccan ‘guestworkers’ who had settled down in
    the district known as Molenbeek, at that time largely deserted. As
    in many other European cities, this desertion had a particular
    socio-economic reason.</p>
    <p>The economic growth of the 50s and 60s saw Belgium’s middle class
    families enter a period of upward social mobility that was followed
    by their move from the central areas of Brussels to the suburbs.
    Simultaneously, the government pursued several bilateral agreements
    to facilitate labour migration, beginning with one with Italy in
    1946, and continuing with others including with Morocco (1964),
    Turkey (1964) and Tunisia (1969) (Martiniello and Rea 2013).
    Blue-collar immigrant workers, like Yunus’ father, subsequently
    settled in central neighbourhoods like Molenbeek, saving the inner
    city from massive depopulation and abandonment (Van Criekingen 2006:
    2). Further migration was generated through family reunifications
    that resulted in migration-dependent communities. As Berger and Mohr
    (2010 [1975]) describe in their poetic account of the male migrant
    experience, apologists for the system argued that the advantages
    were mutual: emigration reduces unemployment and raises wages, a
    shortage of labour in the migrants’ countries of origin (in the case
    of Brussels, mostly Morocco and Turkey) encourages mechanization,
    and migrants acquire industrial skills to take home with them after
    their ‘educative’ experience in industry. The phenomenon was framed
    within academia as modernization theory. Described as a bipolar
    framework that separates push and pull factors of migration, it
    assumed that the movement of labour from areas of origin to areas
    where there is capital brings economic development for both
    (Brettell 2000: 113). While the analyses of modernization theory
    (e.g Rostow 2017 [1960]) focused on how migration facilitates
    progress and modernization, the negative long-term effects for the
    migrants of living in between two countries were not considered.</p>
    <p>One of these effects, that migrants remain unskilled, with
    limited access to language training in their new countries, surfaced
    many times in Yunus’ descriptions of his daily life: ‘I have to go
    and help my parents translating at the town hall’, I heard him say
    more than once, leaving the carpentry studio one or two hours before
    our official end at 5 pm. Living just opposite our working place, he often
    told us about ‘his’ neighbourhood. One scene remained especially
    vivid in my memory: At the very beginning of our training we all
    took a mini-bus with our teacher to drive to the nearest sawmill to
    select and buy wood for the first piece of furniture. Along the way,
    his memory triggered by passing sights that marked his upbringing,
    Yunus commented on every corner. ‘Here you can buy white powder’ –
    shouting and honking from outside – ‘Look over there, they have the
    best weed’ – mixup of voices of parents and kids in front of a
    school – ‘I had a fight there, see, over there, it was last year’,
    he went on and on.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="5"><p><!--5--> Originally in French,
    translation by the author.</p></note> The ride
    was cheerful, Yunus’ descriptions motivated others, the mood built
    up, stories got wilder and more varnished and mostly addressed to
    me, the anthropologist and only woman in the car. Yunus was cheerful
    and enjoyed his telling.</p>
    <p>More than a year later, on Hedi’s terrace, Yunus is rather
    serious: ‘What do you think? How will they look at me now when I
    apply for a job, with my Arab name and Molenbeek as home address?’
    he questioned while lightening his cigarette. While I am drifting
    away, thinking about all the brief encounters with Yunus during my
    research, when I was secretly wishing that he would have told me
    more about himself, he bubbles along. Sooner or later, he assures
    me, he will be self-employed, he will start to be his own boss and
    drive around in a mini-van. ‘Well hopefully you will not have the
    same experience as Hakim, when you drive around Uccle with your
    van!’ mentions Hedi, overhearing the conversation while passing by
    our table. Hakim, like Yunus, born and raised in Molenbeek, works at
    Sibelga, the city’s distribution network operator for electricity
    and natural gas. Within the last months two house owners called the
    police, when Hakim, wearing his official work uniform, tried to
    enter their apartment buildings in Uccle to read the meter.</p>
    <p>While Yunus pays for his daily coffee and quickly packs up his
    things to return to his afternoon shift, we spot Hamuda and Cise,
    smoking their daily lunch-time cigarette, walking in a slow and
    steady pace, despite their being much too late us usual. A
    little jealous, Yunus asks them about their recent carpentry progress.
    ‘Well the centre was closed all the time lately’, complains Hamuda
    about the lock-down and the street barriers that blocked his daily
    lunch break route of cigarette and sandwich buying. ‘Once we started
    to work again, nobody was really bothered and the doors were locked
    from the inside’, he continues. ‘I have not been here for the last
    two weeks’, adds Cise and explains that his doctor prescribed him
    sick-leave during a regular medical control visit, knowing that his
    workplace is in Molenbeek.</p>
    <p>After updating Hamuda and Cise about my recent travels, the
    conferences I had spoken at and how
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">I</hi> had been telling audiences
    about <hi rendition="simple:italic">their</hi> lives, the minute of
    silence that students in Aberdeen held for the victims of the Paris
    attack, Edinburgh castle being lit in the colours of the French
    flag, and my growing anger about the representation of our home in
    the international news, Hedi serves us much-too-sweet peppermint tea
    and proudly shows us a new App on his smartphone. As of late his
    menu is also available online. ‘If your friends do not come here,
    you could at least promote our online-service a bit,’ he winks at
    me. Meanwhile, the market square is slowly taken over by young boys
    and their football games, left over fruits and vegetables are sold
    for half the price and the rusty iron bars create a rhythmic
    clinking while being dismantled and packed. Surrounded by the
    bustling honking of delivery vans, the three of us start one of many
    walks we shared in this city. On our way, we pass by the meat shop
    where I frequently get ingredients for my unsuccessful attempts to
    copy Hedi’s menu. My scooter was parked in the back yard of the very
    same shop during my year at the carpentry centre. Yunus and the
    butcher had brought it there to ‘keep an eye on it’ as they assured
    me, when they found me looking for it, slightly worried, after the
    end of our training day. A few months later it was stolen during the
    day in front of my house in
    Ixelles.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="6"><p><!--6--> One of Brussels’ 19
    municipalities.</p></note> But this, is
    another story; one of many stories that marked this research.</p>
    <p>***</p>
    <p>I decided to start my thesis with this story because in many ways
    it reflects the central ideas of this work: It points to the
    importance of storytelling, using one of its key ingredients, the
    evocation of place (Stoller 2016b). It also puts the reader right
    ‘into place’, to highlight the importance of emplacement (Lems 2013,
    2018) when working with people who find themselves displaced in one
    way or another. This does not mean reverting to the static portrayal
    place-bounded culture, once standard in anthropological research. It
    is rather to draw attention to the fact that even if we are somehow
    displaced, life still unfolds: in forming relationships and
    constructing a home, we shape and are shaped by the place we live
    in. ‘We inhabit our environment:’ as Ingold (2011: 95) has put it,
    ‘we are part of it; and through this practice of habitation it
    becomes part of us too.’</p>
    <p>But although place and its evocation play a central role in this
    work, it is not the geographically bounded ‘site’ that delineated my
    anthropological field but an empirical journey that was marked by
    the people whose paths I crossed, people who let me into their lives
    and walked along with me for a certain length of time. The way I
    stumbled into Yunus on Hedi’s terrace attests to the way this
    journey was often characterized by contingences and coincidences
    that would surface again and again. Finally, the introductory story
    hints at the core aim of this thesis, namely to offer an alternative
    within anthropological research to the overwhelming emphasis on the
    bodily act of craftwork as well as the speechless portrayals of
    migrants, through focusing ‘on the particularity of human existence’
    (Lucht 2012: 15). With the exception of a deeper discussion of
    anthropology and craft, which will be postponed until the next
    chapter, I will retrace each of these points, which form the pillars
    of this work, in this introduction.</p>
  
  <div type="level2" xml:id="brussels-the-most-beautiful-of-all-the-ugly-cities">
    <head>BRUSSELS – THE MOST BEAUTIFUL OF ALL THE UGLY CITIES</head>
    
      <p>I have conducted most of my research in a place I call my home:
      the city of Brussels. Moving from Vienna to Belgium’s capital in
      late 2008, I thought for many years that I knew the place rather
      well. Yet, it was only in January 2014 that I started to really
      explore the other side of the city. I was on my way to apply for a
      one-year- apprenticeship in carpentry in the city’s district
      Molenbeek, the starting point of my research. Leaving from the southern, French-speaking side of
      Europe’s capital, I continued along beautifully coloured old brick
      houses with stunning art nouveau features, past flower shops, the
      smell of fresh croissants in the air, and young families doing
      their weekly shopping at the local organic food market. As I
      carried on towards the northern part of the city, within only 15
      minutes’ bike distance the prospect became greyer and the streets
      vaster. Crossing the concrete lumbering bridge over the canal that
      divides Molenbeek and other similar areas from the centre of
      Brussels, the scenery quickly changes from charmingly narrow red
      brick houses into grim streets, unrestored buildings and run-down
      factories that largely remain
      unoccupied.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="7"><p><!--7--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/2-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/2-2/</ref></p></note></p>
      <p>The district’s nickname, ‘Belgium’s little Manchester’, refers
      to the past when the former village on the outskirts of Brussels
      underwent a gradual process of urbanization and participated in a
      ‘certain global mythology of industrial capitalism’ (Steffens
      2007: 1). Although the past is still inscribed in street names
      like Birmingham Street and abandoned old factory blocks alongside
      the canal, Molenbeek is now more commonly referred to as ‘Little
      Marrakech’ or ‘Little Chicago’, often expressed with a slight
      xenophobic undertone (ibid.: 5). Broken plasma TVs and old plastic
      furniture are popular street decorations. It can indeed give the
      impression of a small-scale version of Paris’
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">banlieues</hi> (suburbs), a parallel
      that has often been drawn (Schram and Fredericks 2016). Yet unlike
      the suburban belt of poverty that surrounds the French capital,
      Molenbeek is only a five-minute walk away from the historical
      centre of the city. In Brussels, one can hardly speak of a
      ‘French-style’ spatial banishment of poor people to the margins,
      when in this case they are located so close to the heart of the
      city. However, as anthropologist Mazzocchetti (2012) points out,
      similar dynamics of ghettoization are at work. Although no
      ‘ghetto’ surrounds the city as such, people living in the
      marginalised areas around the centre are largely separated from
      the rest of the city. In day-to-day life, certain parts of the
      city’s population barely come in contact with each
      other.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="8"><p><!--8--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/3-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/3-2/</ref></p></note></p>
      <p>‘La plus belle des villes
      moches’<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="9"><p><!--9--> ‘The most beautiful
      of all the ugly cities’, translation by the author.</p></note>, as her habitants
      say, sometimes cynically, contains 19 districts with 19
      municipalities and 19 governing mayors. It is as rich in contrast
      and lacking in transparency as its political structure. There is
      for example the district of Saint-Josse-ten-Noode, the smallest
      and economically poorest area of the city, where the second
      generation of Turkish ‘guestworkers’ are jostling for space.
      Bordering Saint-Josse, one can find a different story: the city
      centre with its old town, where the mostly Flemish speaking so
      called ‘Hipsters’ meet in bio-bakeries and organic food chains,
      slowly expanding into newly renovated lofts across the canal.
      There is also Uccle, one of the quietest, greenest and wealthiest
      districts at the other end of the city, home to an increasing
      number of EU deputies and other employees in the orbit of the EU.
      My own story in Brussels started in the two very similar boroughs
      of Ixelles and Saint Gilles, living space for overwhelmingly
      French- speaking students, artists and all sorts of masters of the
      art of living.</p>
      <p>The city’s fragmentation into a ‘montage of contradicting
      pieces’ (D’Hooghe and Bhatia 2007: 75) is not unique to Brussels;
      but in Brussels, this segregation was enhanced by the construction
      of the European Parliament district, which figures quite centrally
      in the landscape of the
      city.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="10"><p><!--10--> The Austrian writer
      Robert Menasse mirrors the fragmented landscape of Brussels as
      well as its influence on the city in his analytical novel
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">Die Hauptstadt</hi> (The capital).
      The novel has been described as the first to be written about the
      European Union, and received the German Book Prize in 2017.</p></note> The presence of a
      large number of generally highly paid international officials has
      contributed to the social and spatial separation of the region.
      The construction of the European Parliament district not only
      enhances this ‘de facto segregation’, but the EU as a global
      stakeholder has also exercised a strong impact on the city’s urban
      environment and its housing market (Corijn et. al 2008). As a
      consequence, districts like Molenbeek remain one of the few areas
      where the economically deprived population can afford to rent a
      place for themselves: like Hamuda who found his very first place
      there; like Cise who woke up many times in a small and freezing
      room in Molenbeek during his first year in Belgium; like Yunus who
      was completely stunned by the green areas in Ixelles, when he
      crossed over to ‘my side’ for the first time. ‘I don’t remember if I have ever
      been in Ixelles before, but I don’t think
      so’,<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="11"><p><!--11--> Originally in
      French, translation by the author.</p></note> he said, surprised
      by my invitation.</p>
      <p>Globalisation, as Lucht (2012: 85) shows, simultaneously
      entails growing connectedness and increasing disconnectedness. The
      EU quarter, a stepping stone for international careers with direct
      public transport access to Uccle and other wealthier areas, is one
      vivid example. Here, ‘intermingling’ is a daily practice, people
      come and go, make connections and travel in and out. A statistic
      showing Brussels to be currently the world’s second most
      cosmopolitan city, after Dubai, recently circulated on the
      Internet (Le Soir 2016). This particular part of the city is
      indeed an example of a modern metropolitan society, where
      transport systems ‘span the globe in a vast network of
      destination-to-destination connections’ (Ingold 2011: 152). But
      what Sanjek (2003: 315) described as ‘postmodern intermingling’ is
      only one side of this story, namely the experience of people who
      are inside ‘the flow’.</p>
      <p>THE WORLDS AND THE
      WORDS<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="12"><p><!--12--> See Hannerz (1997:
      15) ‘The words and the world’.</p></note></p>
      <p>The term ‘flow’ is ‘a way of referring to things not staying in
      their places, to mobility and expansion of many kinds, to
      globalization along many dimensions’, as Hannerz (1997: 4) has
      pointed out. Together with other metaphors such as flux and
      hybridity, ‘flow’ became increasingly used in discussions of
      transnationalism, one of the most prominent theoretical concepts
      in the anthropological study of migration. By briefly discussing
      this influential theory and its broader framework, I aim to
      provide a basis for my own theoretical choices, which I will
      discuss thereafter.</p>
      <p>Emerging in the 90s, the theory of transnationalism emphasizes
      processes whereby migrants operate within social fields that
      transgress geographical, political and cultural borders, taking
      into consideration improved modes of transportation and global
      communication. The geographical and social mobility of migrants
      was placed centre stage, as Brettell (2015: 157) argues: ‘From a
      transnational perspective, migrants are no longer “uprooted”, but rather move freely back
      and forth across international borders’. This description of
      migrants as free movers in a globalized world was embedded in a
      broader change in postmodernist thought that aimed to theorise
      space, place and culture in a new way. Scholars such as Appadurai
      (1995), Feld and Basso (1996), and Gupta and Ferguson (1992),
      theorised space and place not as the neutral backdrop for culture
      but as actively created through cultural processes themselves.
      Transnationalism became ‘part of an effort to reconfigure
      anthropological thinking so that it will reflect current
      transformations in the way in which time and space is experienced
      and represented’ (Glick Schiller et al. 1995: 49). As Gupta and
      Ferguson (1997) point out, to assume that the nation-state is a
      discrete society detracts from the importance of transnational
      connections, and ignores the fact that migrants often live in a
      transnational state. The conflation of country with culture not
      only leads to the portrayal of its people as forming a homogeneous
      community, bound to a specific territory, but has also largely
      contributed to producing the ‘otherness’ of those left
      outside.</p>
      <p>Against this background, transnationalism does indeed provide
      ‘a reasonably comprehensive view of the (relative) coherence and
      the dynamics of larger social and territorial entities than those
      which the discipline has conventionally dealt with’, as Hannerz
      (1997: 4) has stated. But the theoretical shift away from place,
      as one ‘from the closed world to the infinite universe’ (Koyré
      1979: Titlepage), also resulted in a view of people’s lives ‘as
      moving continuously through flexible, open-ended and contested
      space’, as Lems (2014: 317) has put it. Appadurai (1995), one of
      transnationalism’s most prominent proponents, offers an example:
      Developing a framework to understand global cultural flows, he
      proposes that one could see the ‘global cultural economy’ as
      involving five dimensions: ethnoscapes, mediascapes, technoscapes,
      financescapes and ideoscapes. These various ‘scapes’ suggest an
      alternative spatial rendering of the present: one that is not
      fixed as a typical landscape might be, but amorphous and flowing
      in various directions. By following the multiple worlds and scapes
      of people, goods and information spreading around the globe,
      Appadurai shows that modernity exceeds the boundaries and
      determinations of the nation. His work is only one of many
      examples (Augé 1995; Clifford 1997; Gupta and Ferguson 1997) that
      have contributed to the discipline’s new focus on borderless fluidity and movement, and that inherits the feeling of
      ‘uprootedness’ which Berger (2005 [1984]: 55) has prominently
      described as ‘the quintessential experience’ of today’s world.</p>
      <p>Although I support the critique of static models of culture,
      and the deconstruction of the supposedly inherent connection
      between culture and place, I follow Hannerz (1997) in being
      concerned by the terminology of ‘borderless fluidity’ and the way
      it has figured in anthropological discussions of globalization.
      Discussing the keywords of transnational anthropology, Hannerz
      points out that metaphorical evocations of ‘flow’, ‘boundedness’,
      and ‘hybridity’ risk echoing sentiments that many intellectuals
      can identify with, while overlooking the words, ideas, and
      interests of the people with whom we conduct our research. Without
      denying the importance and merits of Appadurai’s early work, the
      focus on trans-border connections, flowing scapes and borderless
      fluidity seemed to have very little to do with the experience of
      those with whom I conducted my research. Instead of freely moving
      back and forth in a globalized world, which might well
      characterize the lives of many people who circulate inside the EU
      orbit in Brussels, the lived worlds of people I got to know
      pointed rather to a continual struggle to craft a life in a place
      and in a world that is littered with borders and obstacles. These
      obstacles manifest themselves in many ways, like the difficulty of
      renting a place outside designated ‘immigrant areas’, the
      challenge of moving around in the city with public transport when
      money is sparse or transport not working due to ‘events’, the
      difficulty of finding work ‘with Molenbeek as a home address’ or
      when having a migrant background, and all the long periods of
      being ‘stuck in a negative zone’ (Lucht 2012: 17) waiting for
      papers and permissions after crossing international frontiers.</p>
      <p>If ‘flow’ suggests some sort of continuity and passage, then
      ‘boundaries’ have to do with discontinuity and obstacles. And
      there were many in the lives not only of Yunus, Cise and Hamuda
      but also of others that I got to know in the carpentry centre in
      Molenbeek. While their stories were different in many ways, global
      modernity and its notion of mobility and travel seemed to be more
      ‘related to the people across the canal’ than a feature of their
      daily life. Without anticipating too much of their stories, I
      think it is safe to say that their experiences mirrored more
      recent academic reflections suggesting that anthropologists have been
      ‘insufficiently attentive to the darker sides of globalization’
      (Appadurai 2006: ix-x) which has led to somewhat utopian
      descriptions of a cosmopolitan world (Glick Schiller
      2015).<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="13"><p><!--13--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/4-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/4-2/</ref></p></note></p>
    
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="crafting-lives-in-a-not-so-mobile-world">
    <head>CRAFTING LIVES IN A NOT SO MOBILE WORLD</head>
    
      <p>Having failed to find a theoretical anchor within transnational
      studies, it was within mobility studies that I discovered a
      framework that goes beyond the initially celebratory view of
      movement. Triggered by transnationalism and postmodern thought, it
      offered a way to address the conditions of life on ‘the other
      side’. Rather than describing free-floating, nomadic and
      borderless existence as the defining character of our age, authors
      of the ‘new mobilities paradigm’ have taken a more nuanced view of
      movement and its shifting meanings. Proponents shifted the
      emphasis towards understanding the relationship between mobility
      and immobility, by putting a stronger emphasis on the social,
      political and economic processes that allow some people to move
      and force others to stay put (e.g. Easthope 2009; Salazar and
      Smart 2012; Sheller and Urry 2006; Urry 2007). Hannan, Sheller and
      Urry (2006) argue that while social life seems increasingly to
      spread its net transnationally, mobilities studies need to develop
      a perspective that problematizes both sedentarist views on place
      and belonging, and deterritorialised perspectives that suggest a
      grand narrative of mobility and fluidity as metaphors for the
      postmodern condition. They therefore suggest that a contemporary
      analysis of mobilities should involve an understanding of the
      diverging consequences of mobility for different people and places
      in what they call the ‘fast and slow lanes of social life’ (ibid.:
      11). Urry (2000, 2007) famously described this relationship as a
      continuous balancing act between mobility and moorings. He argues
      that in an age of globalisation and movement the complexities of
      social life require an analytical point of view that embraces both
      the things that move us and those that keep us anchored in place.
      Mobility and ‘flow’ then might well be an important factor in the
      lives of many people, but so – following Urry – is mooring. Just
      because places are increasingly connected and quickly
      reachable for many does not mean that place is not crucial to how we are
      and how we get to know the world.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="14"><p><!--14--> This paragraph draws
      from material I co-wrote with Lems in an article published during
      the course of my PhD research (Lems and Moderbacher 2016).</p></note></p>
      <p>When a predominant part of life is more about dealing with
      everyday challenges and obstacles, about trying to make sense of
      and construct a life in a place, than it is about freely moving
      back and forth in a globalised world, we have to ‘get back into
      place’ (Casey 1993). This means that we have to take in
      consideration the place that constitutes our mooring, to honour
      the experience of those who are in it, as many have done in more
      recent years (Blau et al. 2002; Casey 1996; Feld and Basso 1996;
      Lems 2018; Stewart 2007). This does not mean going back to a
      static portrayal of one culture in one place, but is rather a
      matter of focusing on how people experience, inhabit and shape the
      particular place they find themselves in. Hence, following Casey,
      the emphasis lies on how place is emergent through experience
      rather than pre- given and solely impinging upon ‘space’. ‘Lived
      bodies’, writes Casey, ‘belong to places and help to constitute
      them. Even if such bodies may be displaced in certain respects,
      they are never placeless’ (Casey 1996: 24).</p>
      <p>‘No one lives in the world in general’, wrote Geertz (1996:
      262) in a similar vein. And so, even if we are somehow displaced,
      we nevertheless inhabit a place by forming relationships,
      constructing a home and shaping a place while being shaped by it.
      With this focus on place, however, I do not intend to refer to a
      certain standstill or stasis in people’s lives as opposed to being
      ‘mobile’. Rather, I follow Ingold, who uses the term ‘wayfaring’
      to describe the embodied experience of movement that ‘unfolds not
      in places but along paths’. Places, he points out, ‘are like
      knots, and the threads from which they are tied are lines of
      wayfaring’ (Ingold 2009: 33). In this story, then, Brussels is
      approached as one of these knots. It is a city that has evolved
      from a sleepy town to one of the most important capitals of the
      world, and to some of its quite particular areas, such as
      Molenbeek, and others that we will explore.</p>
      
    
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="interwoven-trajectories">
    <head>INTERWOVEN TRAJECTORIES</head>
    
      <p>This work then, can also be read as a portrait of a European
      city. It is a portrait constructed out of words, images and
      stories; a portrait that stands in contrast to descriptions of the
      so-called ‘global world’ as well as to the dystopian imaginaries
      that have crucially marked this city and its people:</p>
      <p>Because of its symbolic role as a capital and the large
      presence of religious and cultural minorities […] Brussels has
      become the scene of several dystopian imaginaries about its
      gradual fragmentation […]. Only time will and can tell whether
      alternative narratives will emerge which can grasp this reality in
      terms other than a threatening heterotopia. (Fadil 2014: 326)</p>
      <p>In the story I present here, Brussels figures neither as a
      cosmopolitan space, nor as a dangerous
      dystopia.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="15"><p><!--15--> A more detailed
      discussion of current representations of Brussels and attempts to
      counter them is presented in Chapter 6.</p></note> It attempts to
      shape an alternative narrative, in which the city exists through
      the intimate stories of people that I have come to know; stories
      of Yunus, Hamuda, Cise and others who crossed my path along their
      wayfaring through and beyond this city. It is neither a dangerous
      nor a borderless space but a place on which we put our footprints,
      drawing our lines as much as it draws lines on us. The Brussels I
      discovered, together with the people I got to know, is the café at
      the corner, where Hamuda cried when his sister married in Tunisia
      without his being there, but also his small, first apartment with
      his official name on the doorbell; the many hours of drinking hot
      peppermint tea while telling stories of cold rooms that are
      impregnated in Cise’s bodily memory. Brussels, here, is a place in
      which people like Yunus feel attached to their neighbourhood but
      also struggle with barriers and boundaries, and a strong feeling
      that there is nowhere to go for them outside of their often
      marginalised neighbourhoods, as Mazzocchetti has shown in
      examining young people’s attempts to rationalise the injustice
      they experience (Mazzocchetti 2012). It is a place that provided
      an anchor and a starting point in search for a dignified future
      for Hamuda and Cise, and a place that gave ‘breathing space’ for
      people like the anthropologist Fadil (2008: 17) and myself, both
      escaping from a small countryside village to this multi-layered
      city in search of a more nuanced life. And of course, it is the
      city where we all met to learn a craft together. Some stayed, some
      left, but the people who take part in this narration shared some time in this
      dusty studio from where we started our mental and physical
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">lanterfanten</hi>, as Flemish
      speakers call discovering the ground, wandering around, something
      between strolling and dilly-
      dally.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="16"><p><!--16--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/5-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/5-2/</ref></p></note></p>
      <p>From this carpentry studio in Molenbeek, then, we will follow
      Cise to the Brussels suburb of Overijse, where he makes a life for
      himself and his three sons, we will follow Hamuda to his hometown
      in Tunisia where the blue sky he dreamed about while working the
      wood in Molenbeek transformed his often-pale face. In Molenbeek we
      have met Yunus and we will briefly encounter Tarek as both try to
      make their ways in the place ‘they create for themselves in the
      few rundown and ever so familiar streets in their neighbourhood’
      (Mazzocchetti 2012: 3). And we will also follow some of the paths
      that marked my research, my relations and my way through this
      city. For very different reasons, we all found each other
      entangled in this place, this particular corner of the world that
      serves as home to all of the people whose stories will appear
      along the lines of this
      work.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="17"><p><!--17--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/6-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/6-2/</ref></p></note></p>
      <p>Some of these lines and threads pull through the entire work,
      others were discontinued, like the one that lead me towards Yunus.
      Years after I proudly received my carpentry certificate he still
      works, just as before, in a little corner shop not far from his
      house. Yunus quit the training after about two months. At first,
      he continued passing by for short visits, more and more though we
      met outside, having a coffee and a little chat after I finished
      work. He never really answered my questions as to why he stopped
      the training so suddenly. Once he said, ‘It’s just not my thing’,
      another time he said ‘I have to help my relatives in the corner
      shop, you know’. For a while, when we crossed each other on the
      street by accident, he avoided looking at me. Yunus is one of the
      persons whose paths I shared for only a brief time. They showed me
      how my wayfaring as an anthropologist was often ‘wandering’ or
      ‘errant’ (de Certeau, cited in Ingold 2010a: 130), sinuous instead
      of straight, winding along and often disappointing when my
      academic preconceptions and research priorities did not meet the interests of the people I was interested in. While I was
      eager to discover Yunus’ story in detail, he preferred to keep our
      relationship on the level of superficial encounters, albeit
      knowing about my research and laughing about my sometimes
      seemingly spontaneous note-taking at the beginning of the
      carpentry training. Unlike Yunus, Cise and Hamuda let me be part
      of their lives and told me their stories, although their past
      experiences might have been expected to cause them to refrain from
      doing so. Despite the hardship they faced at times, they kept
      going in telling me their stories as they did with crafting their
      lives as a continuous ‘struggle for being against nothingness –
      for whatever will make life worth living, rather than hopeless,
      profitless and pointless’ (Jackson 2005: x).</p>
      <p>Together with Lucht (2012) and Lems (2013) I follow the lead of
      Jackson’s existential anthropology, which focuses on the question
      of being as a ‘dynamic
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">relationship</hi> between
      circumstances over which we have little control (…) and our
      capacity to <hi rendition="simple:italic">live</hi> those
      circumstances in a variety of ways’ (Jackson 2005: xi, italics in
      original). By extending Sartre’s (1968) work, Jackson points out
      that while ‘our capacity for being is constrained by external
      conditions and engrained habits, it is equally true that these
      limiting conditions are shaped by the ways in which we respond to
      them’ (ibid.: xi). This provides an empirical focus that does not
      reduce the meaning of a person’s existence to either external
      circumstances or inner essence, in a world where money, access to
      education and training, employment and possibilities to move
      forward are not shared by everyone in equal measure. The title of
      this thesis then, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Crafting Lives in
      Brussels: Making and Mobility on the Margins</hi>, highlights its
      theoretical anchoring within mobility studies as well as its
      empirical focus on crafting one’s life through a continuous
      struggle to make something out of the circumstances into which one
      is thrown. In addition, the focus on individual experiences,
      actions, desires and struggles renders people central rather than
      marginal, and gives voice to people who are far too often subsumed
      under such categories as ‘the migrant’ or ‘the refugee’. This
      brings me to the reason for not anchoring this work in the
      subfield of refugee studies, although in legal terms, at least,
      Cise could be described as a ‘refugee’.</p>
    
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="beyond-analytical-categories">
    <head>BEYOND ANALYTICAL CATEGORIES</head>
    
      <p>While migration studies have a long history within
      anthropology, the emergence of the refugee as an analytical
      category is relatively new, as Malkki (1995b) shows by providing
      an historical overview of the sub-discipline of ‘refugee studies’.
      The principal elements of the legal framework for the current
      categorization of refugees emerged in the aftermath of the Second
      World War. International law pertaining to refugees has ‘developed
      within the framework of the international code of Human Rights’
      (Nobel, cited in Malkki 1995b: 500). The basic definition
      contained in the 1951 Geneva Convention Relating to the term
      ‘Refugee’ is as follows:</p>
      <p>[T]he term ‘refugee’ shall apply to any person who: […] owing
      to well- founded fear of being persecuted for reasons of race,
      religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group or
      political opinion, is outside the country of his nationality and
      is unable or, owing to such fear, is unwilling to avail himself of
      the protection of that country; or who, not having a nationality
      and being outside the country of his former habitual residence as
      a result of such events, is unable or, owing to such fear, is
      unwilling to return to it. (UNHCR 2010: 14)</p>
      <p>Over the following two decades, other legal instruments were
      developed, and with the 1967 Protocol, the Geneva Convention
      became a universal instrument relating the status of refugees
      (UNHCR 1989). The disciplines of international relations and peace
      studies, along with a large body of literature and documentation
      produced by the UNHCR, have helped to develop refugee studies as a
      field, especially from the 1980s onwards (Malkki 1995b: 507). My
      aim here is not to summarize work in this field or to present its
      intellectual agenda, but rather to examine briefly one of its most
      influential concepts, namely that of ‘the refugee experience’
      (Stein 1981). Proposing to examine the experience of refugees as a
      category, Stein sought to characterize refugee lives as passing
      through a more or less fixed sequence of stages, or ‘recurring
      phenomena with identifiable and often identical patterns of
      behaviour and sets of causalities’ (Stein 1981: 321). Following
      Malkki, I find this attempt to reduce the refugee condition to a
      single common denominator to be problematic. It writes and
      photographs different people into a category that share ‘a
      culture’, ‘an identity’ and ‘a social world’ (Malkki 1995b: 511).
      This categorization of refugees into one kind of ‘people’ has real
      consequences in everyday life that appear to justify the sealing
      of borders and the need to control movement, as I will point out
      in Chapter three.</p>
      <p>In addition, the distinction commonly made between refugees and
      migrants, according to which the former are supposed to have left
      their home region involuntarily whereas the latter have left by
      choice, is rather simplistic, as is the corresponding distinction
      between political and economic migrants. These distinctions are
      facile in a world where movements have ‘extraordinarily diverse
      historical and political causes and involve people who, while all
      displaced, find themselves in qualitatively different situations
      and predicaments’ (Malkki 1995b: 496). To oppose free choice to
      forced movement leaves out important questions about the
      conditions that make movement possible and desirable for some and
      impossible for others. By questioning these categories, I do not
      intend to blur, obscure or undermine the extreme hardship of
      displaced people, refugees waiting for decades in camps around the
      world or in the asylum system in state-sanctioned poverty and
      exclusion. But, following Malkki (1995b: 496), I refuse to take
      these categories, of the ‘refugee’ and the ‘migrant’, as given.
      Rather, following recent debates on migrant and refugee labelling
      processes (Fassin and d’Halluin 2005; Kibreab 2000; Zetter 2007),
      I argue that regardless of how people are externally categorized,
      it is by focusing on the individual experience of crafting a life
      that we can counter generalizing reductions and homogenizing
      images. Therefore, anchoring this work in existential anthropology
      makes it possible to draw people out of their ascribed status and
      bring to the fore ‘the <hi rendition="simple:italic">presence</hi>
      of the human subject in academic research and writing’ (Jackson
      and Piette 2015: 3, italics in original).</p>
      <p>In his own work, Jackson has focused on ‘critical events’
      (2005, cf. Das 1995) and on storytelling (2002), in order to
      escape generalizing reductions and to broach the question of being
      as a relationship between the forces that act upon us and our own
      capacity to act. Others have found their own ways. Lucht (2012),
      influenced by Kleinman (2006), focuses similarly on critical
      events, examining the plight of West African immigrants in their
      efforts to secure a desired life. Lems (2013, 2018) presents a
      collection of stories by three Somali refugees in Australia, using
      a compelling narration throughout her contribution, while
      Desjarlais has developed what he calls an ‘intensity-centered
      phenomenology’. Prioritizing this method over a ‘person-centered
      ethnography’, he argues, lends priority to the ‘gamut of forces
      and sensations’ (Desjarlais 1996: 70) that course through the
      lives of inhabitants of a shelter for the homeless and mentally ill in downtown Boston
      (1997). He foregrounds a phenomenological approach that he
      understands as a ‘method of inquiry […] that works to understand
      and describe in words phenomena as they appear to the
      consciousness of certain peoples’ (2003: 6). Following Desjarlais’
      approach, the phenomena most in question in my work are the
      challenges and difficulties, but also the triumphs in achieving
      small successes, while making a life on the margins, regarding the
      continual quest to move forward and to find a place for oneself in
      this world. My approach could be described as a blend of
      ‘intensity-centered phenomenology’ and ‘person-centered
      ethnography’. While at times, I followed forces and sensations
      that triggered deeper discussions and led to new paths, the two
      core chapters of this work mirror a person-centred ethnography
      that reflects the deep engagement with Hamuda Djerbi and Cise
      Ibrahima. All of these chapters, though, underpin my conviction
      that ‘no human being comes to a knowledge of himself or herself
      except through others’ (Jackson 1995: 118). As much as we mutually
      inhabit the same world, we only exist in intersubjectivity. I
      consider this as a two-fold movement that transforms and returns
      one changed to oneself. This practice also largely determined my
      approach towards the anthropological field.</p>
    
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="notes-on-the-field">
    <head>NOTES ON ‘THE FIELD’</head>
    <quote>
      <p>Throughout the history of anthropology, the term ‘field’ has
      been used to describe the place where anthropologists do their
      research. It connoted a geographical space set apart from the
      urban, probably agrarian, or ‘maybe even “wild”’, as Gupta and
      Ferguson (1997: 8) state. But as anthropological thinking was
      reconfigured in the 1990s, and the ‘assumed isomorphism of space,
      place and culture’ (Gupta and Ferguson 1992: 7) came to be
      increasingly questioned, so too was the approach to ‘the field’ as
      a frame with clearly defined borders. Gupta and Ferguson (1992,
      1997) questioned representations of territorially fixed
      communities, drawing attention to the power issues involved, while
      others have questioned the strict geographical and cultural
      borders of the field (Appadurai 1996) and its separation from the
      personal life of the researcher (Amit 2000). Following these
      reflections, I do not conceptualize the field as an entity
      separated by geographical distance, nor do I assume that the
      researcher’s life entails an independent set of relationships. I
      believe that the concern with boundaries should be an empirical one and not determined
      by the length of a journey to a faraway place. Accordingly, my
      field was not framed by its geographical boundaries but defined by
      the people whose paths I crossed and shared. My boundaries were
      empirical, not geographical, following people’s lives, drawing
      lines in and outside Brussels together. As I already noted, this
      is not to say that place as such is unimportant. But while
      Brussels as a place to live in, and its evocation, form an
      important part of this story, I use the term ‘field’ more in a
      metaphorical way to suggest a place where things are grown.
      Similar to planting and growing seeds, both I and the people with
      whom I conducted research grew through our mutual engagement. Its
      fruits were manifold and left marks on all of us, some deeper than
      others. While Cise and Hamuda have become friends, and remain part
      of my life, there were people like Tarek and Yunus from whom I
      grew apart. Nevertheless, they left marks in my research and my
      life and I believe I did the same for them, being the first person
      out of their ‘usual environment’ they ‘kind of got to know’, as
      they both assured
      me.<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="18"><p><!--18--> See:
      <ref target="http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/7-2/">http://www.christinemoderbacher.com/7-2/</ref></p></note></p>
      <p>My own path and my self-presentation as an anthropologist and
      filmmaker played a crucial role in building my relationships with
      the people entangled in this ‘field of growth’. As
      anthropologists, I believe, our work is deeply intertwined with
      the trajectories of our own lives, as I will show in the following
      chapter. It is partly a feeling of ‘strangeness’, of not living in
      my country of origin myself, of searching for a new home, that
      marks my approach towards this research. As Okely (1992) has
      argued, autobiographical reflexivity is an integral element of
      fieldwork, and I believe that where our attention goes and whom we
      work with depends on the intellectual as well as the personal
      baggage – our own shadow as Crapanzano (1986) would say – that we
      carry along with us. <note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="19"><p><!--19--> See Crapanzano 1986,
      p. 44 of this work.</p></note>
      Any account of the way ethnographic inquiry is conducted should
      thus simultaneously be an account of the researcher in the field
      (Lucht 2012: 14). I too have changed countries, have struggled to
      adapt and have tried to make sense of places I have come to live
      in. By no means, though, do I want to equate my comparatively
      privileged experience of moving places to the experience of the people who became part of my work. As Hooks (1992) has
      pointed out, an identification with marginalized people denies
      their ontological existence and only recognises the other as an
      extension of oneself. In the relational dynamics of imperialism,
      she interprets this narcissistic form of defensive recognition as
      ‘eating the other’ (Hooks, cited in Haaken and O’Neill 2014: 84).
      Considering that the majority of people who conducted the
      carpentry apprenticeship with me originally come from places that
      have suffered a great deal from imperialistic forces, I consider
      this awareness to be an intrinsic part of my work.</p>
      <p>AN APPRENTICESHIP IN CARPENTRY AND LIFE – SETTING AND
      OVERVIEW</p>
      <p>My fieldwork officially started in September 2014, in a
      carpentry centre next to Molenbeek’s central square Les Etangs
      Noirs (Black Ponds). Since its creation in 1962, the International
      Service for Research, Education and Social Action – SIREAS
      asbl<note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="20"><p><!--20--> asbl refers to
      “association sans but lucrative” - non-profit-making organization
      (translation by the author).</p></note> – has organized
      activities to facilitate the integration of foreigners. One of the
      organisation’s most advertised aims within their lifelong learning
      program is to improve the chances of the marginalized population
      within the labour market. Although not exclusively designed for
      foreigners, most participants in the program are either not born
      in Belgium or second generation immigrants. The activities offered
      are supported by the National Ministry of Culture as well as the
      European Union. To be able to participate in one of SIREAS’
      training courses, a person must pass a written and oral entrance
      exam and must be registered at the Brussels job searching
      institution Actiris, which often also sent participants for
      training. The setting of my apprenticeship, then, was very
      different from those described in many other accounts within the
      subfield of the anthropology of craft (Cohen 2010; Dilley 1989;
      Marchand 2008; Singleton 1989; Venkatesan 2010), as I will show in
      more detail in the following chapter. Most of the apprentices I
      worked with did not choose to learn woodwork out of a desire to
      engage with this particular material, but were dependent on state benefits that were linked to their presence and
      success in the training. That the training was more a requirement
      than a way to follow one’s passion for a craft, surfaced from the
      very start of the training.</p>
      <p>There were ten of us at the beginning of the course. Most did
      not want to appear with their names in this work and remained
      ‘curiously distant’ towards ‘this anthropologist’ interested in
      carpentry. During the first day, we had to introduce ourselves to
      each other quickly, each of us standing next to our assigned
      working desk. There were nine men, a woman whom I will call Anna,
      and myself. Anna, a single mother of two boys, proved to be the
      most dedicated and persistent during the entire year. There was
      Malek, <note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="21"><p><!--21--> Name changed by the
      author.</p></note> a funny
      40-year-old man whose ‘Ataturk like moustache’, as he called it
      himself, was surrounded by a smiley, likeable face that showed his
      sense of humour immediately. Malek was living in Saint Jose with
      his wife and three kids. Due to his weak French writing skills and
      constant nostalgic descriptions about ‘his’ village in Turkey, I
      assumed for quite a while that he had only recently come to
      Belgium. Only midway through the training did I find out that he
      was born in Brussels and had lived there all his life. There was
      Viorel from Rumania, and Tarek whom I will introduce in the
      following chapter. There was Yunus, who immediately caught my
      attention by stealing twenty euros out of my pocket unnoticed,
      handing them back to me in front of everybody with a proud smile.
      There was Cise, a calm, friendly Guinean in his mid-fifties, whom
      I did not really notice at first. Two young men of Moroccan
      descent living in Molenbeek, one of them who left the training
      soon after its initiation, a young Belgian and myself, an
      anthropologist and filmmaker, completed the group. Explaining my
      attempt to work alongside them while doing ‘paid’ research, I
      could see their wondering thoughts written in their surprised
      faces. They all looked at me confused, until Malek said: ‘What?
      So, you mean you have a job already but you want to come here
      working every day at 8.30 am? You must be crazy!’ His reaction
      caused shared laughter that was interrupted by a bell that
      signalled the daily morning break at 10.30. While drinking the
      watery coffee that was offered twice a day in the courtyard of the
      two-story building, Anna and I noticed that we were the only two women amongst 45 men
      that gathered in the centre to learn carpentry, bricklaying,
      mechanics or plumbing. ‘I am very happy that you are crazy!’ Anna
      laughed at me while smoking her cigarette, looking insecurely at
      all the men around us.</p>
      <p>I was not only one out of two women in the centre and within
      the carpentry apprentices, I was also one of the very view
      participants who lived in Ixelles, which caused equal astonishment
      and mirrored the aforementioned fragmentation of Brussels. As an
      academic and a researcher, I enrolled on this apprenticeship with
      an aim that clearly differed from those of the other participants.
      <note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="22"><p><!--22--> See also Gowlland
      2009, Venkatesan 2010, and Chapter 2 of this work.</p></note> Although it was
      arranged with the teacher and the director of the centre at the
      beginning of my fieldwork that I would have to commit to the rules
      of the apprenticeship, including taking out work insurance, being
      present full-time and participating in exams during the year, so
      as not to disturb the daily working life in the centre, I was not
      likely to make my living working with the craft and did not
      envisage myself spending the rest of my life in this profession,
      as some of the other participants did at the beginning of their
      training (see also Cooper 1989: 138). I was not financially
      dependent on the results of my carpentry work and could approach
      the training with much greater ease than the others. Being a woman
      in an almost exclusively male environment certainly also
      influenced daily interactions and occasionally led to frustrations
      and difficulties during days when gender-related jokes and
      comments were aplenty.</p>
      <p>Besides these differences that made it difficult for me to find
      my place within the group, the beginning also brought other
      surprises. In preparation for my fieldwork, I had read a lot about
      working together with others, and about the conversations it could
      potentially trigger. Wachowich (1999), for example, describes how
      stitching skin garments together with Inuit women in the Canadian
      High Arctic triggered the telling of stories. But the setting I
      found myself in was different. Learning to work with wood demanded
      a lot of concentration and generally left little time and space
      for talking. The noisy machines played their part. While the
      ‘fieldwork folder’ on my computer’s desktop contains many archived photographs of
      blistered hands battling with the wood and proud smiles next to
      the first achieved pieces of furniture, an entire day of working
      inside the studio might be rewarded with only a view lines of
      field- notes, quickly scribbled on paper once I was home. Contrary
      to what I had read prior to my fieldwork (Benjamin 1968; Leslie
      2010), discussion on recurring topics as well as events that
      marked our days mostly took place outside the workshop. Once it
      became apparent that participation in an apprenticeship was not my
      main method, as I shall show in Chapter two, but rather served as
      an entry point into the lives of the makers, these difficulties
      and initial disappointments became less relevant. Nevertheless, I
      did continue working alongside the others during an intense year
      of learning and many intense days of – at least for me –
      previously unexperienced tiredness.</p>
      <p>The apprenticeship comprised 36 hours per week, was structured
      similarly to an academic calendar (with a one-week break during
      Christmas and Easter), and ended in June 2015. During the year, we
      mostly worked in the carpentry studio, but also had French, IT and
      ‘citizenship lessons’ that included an introduction to Belgian
      work practices and regular excursions (e.g., a visit to the
      Belgium Parliament Building). In this work, I am using
      ‘apprenticeship’ and ‘training’ to describe the program. Although
      it might be difficult to define the training program as an
      apprenticeship in the classical sense, whose more traditional
      meaning refers to working alongside a master, using only the word
      ‘training’ would not be sufficient. This might also be linked to a
      different meaning contained in the word “apprenticeship” in
      English and “<hi rendition="simple:italic">apprentissage</hi>” in
      French. While in French the term seems to be used as a more
      general term for learning, it is much more specific to a certain
      institutional arrangement in English. While the structure and the
      other classes mentioned above might better fit the term training,
      the learning process in carpentry rather resembled an
      institutionalized apprenticeship. We were working alongside the
      teachers, at times manufacturing furniture items on order as in a
      ‘real’ workshop. In addition, the teachers as well as the
      participants themselves used both terms: in French,
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">apprentissage</hi> and
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">formation</hi> (training).</p>
      <p>Anticipating the start of my fieldwork, I had walked in
      Brussels, especially in the area surrounding the carpentry studio,
      many times before the beginning of the training, and had visited
      the centre twice to enrol myself. The first two months in the
      studio were marked by an initial excitement about woodwork and the
      focus on learning a skill, which I aimed to capture on camera. I
      am not the first anthropologist to have given in to this initial
      excitement. As Gowlland (2015a: 274) states, ‘The first encounter
      with craftwork in the field often leads to enthusiastic, albeit
      relatively unreflexive, initial attempts to produce images of
      craft’. My own, partly unreflexive attempts to produce images of
      craft were suddenly interrupted by Tarek, one of the participants,
      whose words led me to reflect more widely on my role as a
      filmmaker and anthropologist. By retracing the event that led my
      research into new paths, Chapter 2 discusses the resulting shift
      of attention from an anthropology of craft to the crafting of an
      anthropology that is part and parcel of our common life. By
      contrasting the overwhelming focus, within the anthropology of
      craft, on the bodily act of craftwork with the lives of the people
      I worked with, I will show how my inquiry came to be extended
      beyond the physical confines of the workshop into other areas,
      like memories, worries, struggles and dreams, offering an insight
      into the existential demands of human life. With this, Chapter 2
      forms the basis of a thesis that aims to shed light on people as
      ‘skilled makers of a place for themselves in the world’ (Sennett
      2008: 13).</p>
      <p>While Chapter 2 portrays my epistemological path towards the
      maker’s life trajectories, Chapter 3 offers a deeper insight into
      life storytelling as an anthropological genre. After discussing
      the need to write against universalized conditions, I will spell
      out some of the main characteristics that frame this method, that
      ‘provides a model of research’ that ‘depends on ongoing
      collaboration between interviewer and interviewee’ (Cruikshank
      1990: 1), and retrace my steps from words to text. By critically
      discussing previous works that influenced and inspired my own
      writing, I aim to illuminate the choices I had to make along the
      way. As many others before, I had trouble transforming my
      informants’ lives as they were lived into stories, once I
      dedicated myself to writing. By laying open some of these
      difficulties as well as the solutions I found, I aim to beat a
      path towards the core of this thesis: the life stories of Hamuda
      Djerbi and Cise Ibrahima. Along with Desjarlais (2003: 5) and others whose work I will discuss later on, I am convinced that
      anthropologists should not limit themselves solely to the study of
      broader social or cultural phenomena, ‘that the drift of
      narratives often proves to be more illuminating than sweeping
      statements; and that one can sometimes learn more by tending to
      particulars within the folds of the general.’ This is not, of
      course, to discard a more standard mode of anthropological writing
      nor to question the need of analytical tools and theoretical
      insights. I only argue that on some occasions, and around some
      people, a story is necessary – a story not rendered into
      information, but one that is just that: a story to be told.
      Stories, as Stoller (2016a, b) says, have the ability to remain
      open to the world because they touch upon fundamental issues of
      the human condition, things that matter to most of us like home, a
      sense of belonging and the desire for a better life. Such ‘things
      that matter’ lie at the heart of anthropological concern.</p>
      <p>Chapters 4 and 5 are an attempt to put these thoughts into
      practice. They are dedicated to the words of Cise Ibrahima and
      Hamuda Djerbi. The chapters offer an alternative focus to existing
      research on craft and migration by zooming in on their life
      trajectories through their own words. In keeping their stories
      separated I follow Patai, who approaches an ‘individual life story
      as a document that is itself unique and highly valuable, one we
      must not too readily leap over in pursuit of the generalization’
      (Patai 1988: 143). This permits a close look at the peculiarities
      of their individual life paths and their specific reactions to
      them but also points at commonalities that speak for more than
      their individual lives. Their stories are different in many ways,
      as we will come to know, but they both shed light on how crafting
      one’s life on the margins of a European city is actually done. The
      two chapters retell Cise’s and Hamuda’s life stories from an early
      age on to the present, more than a year after the carpentry
      training, and are the products of many hours of storytelling,
      walking and working together. The result is an attempt at
      ethnographic writing that proposes a poetic translation that does
      justice to the intersubjective experience of narration. The
      willingness of Cise and Hamuda to let me into their lives demanded
      that I share my life with them, as they did with mine. The
      chapters thus also shed light on the dialogical nature of bringing
      out stories. I have tried my best to include this process into the
      writing. The result might be troubled, in one way or another, and
      might not always be successful. I am, however, taking this risk
      deliberately, convinced as I am that we need greater
      experimentation in anthropological writing.</p>
      <p>Chapter 6 grew out of a strong need to provide a counter-image
      to forces that increasingly surfaced during my time in Brussels:
      the growing national and international reputation of this city and
      its consequences for the people that call it their home. While the
      events surfaced only occasionally inside the carpentry studio,
      they triggered a re-visit to ‘the field’ a couple of months later.
      The ‘intensities felt’ (Desjarlais 1996) during this encounter are
      evoked in the story with which I began this work. While the video
      and photo camera did not play the role inside the carpentry studio
      that I had originally intended, as explained in Chapter 2, the new
      eruptions seemed to render my research into one of those places
      where the camera ‘seems to be necessary’ (Rouch, cited in Henley
      2009: 312). This, and other reasons for my decision to work on a
      multi-modal approach and representation of my work, form the core
      of this chapter.</p>
      <p>Chapter 7, entitled ‘Little to go on with’, refers to two
      challenges of this work. The first is the difficulty to go on with
      a story once words have fallen silent. The second relates to the
      hardship of daily life once training is done. By casting my
      ethnographic eye on Cise’s lifeworld, the chapter questions how to
      move forward after an intense period of hopes and dreams, when
      reality seems to hinder one’s path on all fronts. Without
      bracketing out Cise’s effort to counter his circumstances and to
      craft a life for himself, the chapter suggests a less romantic
      reading of learning a craft and the consequences it entails. It
      also calls for deeper scrutiny of the long-term effects of a life
      that is characterized by recurring phases of immobility and
      ‘stuckedness’ (Hage 2009a).</p>
      <p>The Concluding Remarks summarize the main threads of this story
      and suggest how the study might contribute to the discipline of
      anthropology as well as to the lives of the people involved in it.
      While some things like the training and this thesis had come to an
      end, others are ongoing, and have led to new endeavours and
      further questions. They will be foreshadowed in the last
      chapter.</p>
      <p>Taking into account the reflections presented above, this
      thesis addresses the question of how people living on the margins
      of a European city experience and narrate their lives, and how
      this is influenced by their participation in carpentry training,
      whether as a trainee like Cise, or as an intern like Hamuda. It
      aims to explore what it really means to craft one’s life through a
      continuous struggle of making something out of the circumstances
      in which one is thrown. This work thus offers an anthropological
      inquiry into the individual life trajectories of two people and
      how they each makes sense of them, using participant observation,
      life storytelling and audio-video devices as the main
      methodological tools. The intention is not to present a study of
      craft, or of migration. It is rather to get a glimpse into the
      direct experience of certain individuals in their struggle for a
      decent life.</p>
      <p>A PORTRAIT CONSTRUCTED OUT OF WORDS, IMAGES AND SOUNDS</p>
      <p>Although I approached my topic and the people entwined with it
      mostly through participant observation and storytelling, my
      practices along the way – my methods – varied from stage to stage,
      from setting to setting and from person to person. Every chapter,
      then, is accompanied by a deeper reflection on actions generated
      from the needs and intensities felt. I understand, following
      Ingold, that to carry out participant observation is ‘to attend to
      what others are doing or saying and to what is going on around and
      about; to follow along where others go and to do their bidding,
      whatever this might entail and wherever it might take you’ (Ingold
      2014: 389), and will come back to this mode of inquiry in the
      conclusion. As I will argue in detail in Chapter 2, anthropology –
      the way I would like to practise it – does not always require a
      strict methodological frame, but a series of skills, tensions and
      vocabularies through which we can try to articulate some knowledge
      of the world and thereby correspond with it (Cubero 2015; Ingold
      2008). From the perspective of an anthropology that pays attention
      to what the world has to tell (Chapter 2), there is not one
      primary tool like the pen, or the camera. All that is required is
      that the tools we use are up to our task.</p>
      <p>Such a way of working implies a particular conception of
      presentation. Mirroring the different methods and tools I used
      during my work, the final form of this thesis is a montage of text, photographs and short films. In Chapter 6 I
      present the reasons for this choice in more detail. This reflects
      my academic as well as artistic approach, considering every
      project as a new experience, bringing into play a dialogue between
      form and content, ethics and aesthetics, and political and
      poetical realms (see Van Lancker 2012). In this sense, every
      chapter, as well as the online platform
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">Invisible Brussels</hi>, is an
      experiment that does not test a hypothesis but rather functions as
      a new opening. On some occasions, I wrote poems that found their
      way into this thesis. The making of the installation-piece that
      Cise and I prepared together for an exhibition is described in
      Cise’s story (Chapter 4).
      <note xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" n="23"><p><!--23--> Also see Appendix,
      Exhibition Programme <hi rendition="simple:italic">KFI – Knowing
      From the Inside</hi>.</p></note> The chapters, some more
      narrative than others, mix with videos, sound pieces and photos
      made by Cise and myself that tell their own story and, as I hope,
      evoke a sense of people and place in this work. The online
      platform <hi rendition="simple:italic">Invisible Brussels</hi>
      bunches together the photos, sound pieces and videos. Putting this
      material online allows for easy and free access as well as the
      option to continue the work beyond this thesis. Following the
      links to <hi rendition="simple:italic">Invisible Brussels</hi>,
      provided in the footnotes, is one way to read this entire work.
      While the online project is described in more detail in Chapter 6,
      I will briefly embed the chosen form of this entire thesis within
      the discipline of anthropology – in particular with regard to
      crossovers with the domain of visual anthropology which has
      influenced my career to a large extent – before concluding this
      introduction.</p>
    </quote>
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="common-potentials---writing-for-a-new-arena-of-debate">
    <head>COMMON POTENTIALS - WRITING FOR A NEW ARENA OF DEBATE</head>
    <quote>
      <p>In addition to its contribution to the body of work on mobility
      and craft, this thesis also experiments with the ‘form’ of
      anthropological work. To argue for this choice, I will first give
      a brief historical overview of the development of, and crossovers
      between, filmic and textual representation within anthropology.
      Prioritizing similarities rather than differences between modes of
      representation within the discipline, as others have done before
      (Cubero 2015; Grimshaw and Hart 1994; Marcus 1990), I will discuss
      work that has been influential for my own project.</p>
      <p>In the last decades, the use of tools such as the camera and
      sound recorder, but also the pencil to draw or the brush to paint,
      have become significant research tools for anthropologists as well
      as for its transmission to a broader audience. New sensorial,
      narrative and collaborative strategies have been developed and
      have contributed to the refreshment of our discipline. The
      relevance of the ‘integration’ of these practices into
      anthropology – in its original Latin sense of
      ‘<hi rendition="simple:italic">integrare</hi>: refreshing,
      restoring’ – has long since entered mainstream academic thinking.
      The time of ranking written as against audio-visual outcomes of
      research is past: it is no longer productive and only leads to
      methodological dichotomies that do nothing to move our discipline
      forward. Consequently, it is not my concern here whether one form
      is more suitable than others to present the anthropological
      endeavour; nor do I want to give the impression that the filmed
      image has a ‘limited capacity to convey ethnographic knowledge’,
      as Hastrup (1992) has claimed. The idea of the poverty of the
      image, I argue, stems from a lack of familiarity with the art of
      image-making, and Hastrup’s work offers a case in point. In trying
      to capture the ‘male ambience’ of a ram exhibition in Iceland,
      Hastrup opposes a text, a genre she knows very well, to a picture
      that she has taken without any consideration of the art of
      photography. Based on this experience alone, she went on to
      compare the thickness of ethnographic description afforded by
      written modes of presentation to the thinness of visual accounts.
      But as Cox and Wright (2012) point out in their critique, the
      thinness of the image, in Hastrup’s hands, owes less to the medium
      itself than to her failure to engage in any depth with the art of
      photography, instead reducing the act of image-making to the
      technical aspect of pressing a button.</p>
      <p>This example is only one of many that shows the apparent
      mismatch between different tools to lie in an unequal familiarity
      with their respective crafts. As much as anthropologists complain
      about how ‘their method’ – ethnography – has been exported to
      other disciplines without deeper reflection, the craft of
      photography can be, and has been, equally abused by
      anthropologists who are not well practised in it. We cannot aim
      for the successful integration of non-textual representation
      without a critical engagement with the specific craft we use, as
      Pink (2004) has shown. Perhaps for Hastrup’s project, text was the
      right choice. But it is not possible to draw a wider conclusion
      from her experience. While some anthropologists, like Hastrup,
      have emphasised the merits of text, and others to the merits of
      film (MacDougall 2006;</p>
      <p>Mead 2003 [1975]; Pink 2006) or sound (Cox 2010; Feld 1982;
      Feld and Brenneis 2004), I side with Marcus, who writes that:</p>
      <p>A new arena of debate is needed in which the differences
      between these two media of representation and their relative
      possibilities in reconstituting the idea of what anthropological
      knowledge is, or should be, can be discussed from a starting
      position which recognizes a certain identity between them as well
      as an equality of intellectual standing. (Marcus 1990: 2)</p>
      <p>Marcus’ claim was taken up by Grimshaw and Hart, who insist
      that if we are to work towards an anthropology of the future, we
      should talk not about ‘what we are
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">against</hi>, but what we are
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">for</hi>’ (Grimshaw and Hart 1994:
      257, italics in original). They suggest that the strength and
      creative force of anthropology lies within ‘a more flexible,
      constructive approach to learning about the world’ (ibid.: 1994:
      259). More recently, the discussion was taken up by Cubero (2015),
      who also mentions the common potentials of different modes of
      presentation. Cubero suggests that we should concentrate on making
      visible the process of gaining knowledge rather than following
      specific theoretical and methodological protocols. Approaching
      anthropology as a creative practice, he proposes a common ground
      ‘from where anthropologists can engage with ethnographies made in
      different media’ (Cubero 2015: 366). In Chapter 2, I will return
      to this point in discussing my own reflections concerning this
      topic.</p>
    </quote>
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="crafting-representations-poetics-of-ethnography">
    <head>CRAFTING REPRESENTATIONS – POETICS OF ETHNOGRAPHY</head>
    
      <p>Embedded in a more general epistemological crisis within the
      humanities about Western constructions and the representation of
      otherness (e.g. Fabian 1983; Fanon 1952; Said 1978; Spivak 1987),
      a debate was triggered within the discipline that discussed,
      amongst other things, forms of ethnographic writing, reflexivity
      and authority, objectivity, the claim to truth and the broader
      concept of culture in society (Abu Lughod 1993; Clifford and
      Marcus 1986; Marcus 1986; Mohanty 1991; Pratt 1986). Without
      suggesting that other topics are less worthy of investigation, it
      is the question of how the result should be represented
      ethnographically – the poetics of ethnography – that is of
      importance for this reflection and subsequently to my work.</p>
      <p>Thirty years after its initial publication, Clifford and
      Marcus’ edited volume <hi rendition="simple:italic">Writing
      Culture. The Poetics and Politics of Ethnography</hi> (1986) still
      remains an important contribution to the ‘writing culture’ debate, which has had a
      long-lasting effect on the discipline. Clifford argues against the
      transformation of ethnographic experience into data and highlights
      the partial truth of ‘ethnographic information’. He further
      identifies these so called ‘informations’ as ‘inescapably
      allegorical’ (1986: 99) and urges the discipline to take
      responsibility for the systematic constructions of others and of
      ourselves through others (1986: 121). Tyler also demands a change
      in the textual conversion. It is however not only the form of the
      text, but also the cooperation between ethnographers and
      informants, that he regards as decisive (Tyler 1986: 127). Instead
      of representation, he proposes the concept of evocation that he
      describes as neither presentation nor representation:</p>
      <p>It presents no objects and represents none, yet it makes
      available through absence what can be conceived but not presented.
      It is thus beyond truth and immune to the judgment of performance.
      (Tyler 1986: 123)</p>
      <p>Agreeing with Tyler’s and Clifford’s theoretical reflections
      but missing concrete examples of the consequences for producing
      anthropological work, it was Crapanzano’s contribution that caught
      my attention: In it, he compares the anthropologist to the
      trickster who promises to Hermes not to lie, but neither to tell
      the entire truth:</p>
      <p>He presents languages, cultures, and societies in all their
      opacity, their foreignness, their meaninglessness; then like the
      magician, the hermeneut, Hermes himself, he clarifies the opaque,
      renders the foreign familiar, and gives meaning to the
      meaningless. He decodes the message. He interprets. (Crapanzano
      1986: 51)</p>
      <p>As Geertz had already proposed (1988), Crapanzano deals with
      the process of textualization as an interpretation by the
      researcher and argues for the visualization of this ‘shadow’ in
      our work. This so-called reflexivity, described by Crapanzano as
      ‘shadow’, has remained one of the most durable outcomes of the
      ‘writing culture’ debate; but while reflection on the
      anthropological self is now often considered an integral part of
      disciplinary practice, the performative aspect of text-making has
      received less attention.</p>
      <p>In parallel, questions relating to representation in
      anthropology were already being posed by filmmaker
      anthropologists, and had been for some time. This points towards
      the ongoing relationship of interaction and impact that written
      ethnography and ethnographic film have long shared (Lutkehaus and Cool 1999).
      Jean Rouch, called by many ‘the father of visual anthropology’,
      already attempted to enter a dialogue with his subjects on camera
      and to insert it into the representation of his work in his early
      film <hi rendition="simple:italic">Jaguar</hi> (1967). In this
      example, Rouch records the main protagonists discussing their
      hunting traditions while watching the footage together. He then
      uses the track as a voice-over for the final film. Later on, David
      and Judith MacDougall re- used the recorded conversations with
      their participants for their African trilogy
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">Turkana Conversations</hi> (1989) in
      a similar way (see Lutkehaus and Cool 1999: 119). All three
      filmmakers practiced early attempts of image-making that reflect
      the dialogical engagement of their work long before the topic
      reached the level of theoretical attention within the written
      domain.</p>
      <p>At the same time that these developments in visual anthropology
      were going on, throughout the second half of the
      20<hi rendition="simple:superscript">th</hi> century, some
      anthropologists were also tempted to write in a different manner –
      albeit with little recognition from academia. Laura Bohannan
      published her work <hi rendition="simple:italic">Return to
      Laughter</hi> in 1954 under the pseudonym Elenore Smith Bowen, to
      escape the denunciation of her colleagues. In one of
      anthropology’s first attempts at novelistic writing, she lets
      others talk through polyphony and dialogical presentation. Only
      Barbara Myerhoff’s book <hi rendition="simple:italic">Number our
      days. A triumph of continuity and culture among Jewish old people
      in an urban ghetto</hi> (1978), about ageing within the
      anthropologist’s own community in California, received any
      recognition from within academia. The book resulted in a film
      that, up to now, is the only example coming from within the
      discipline of anthropology that received an Academy Award (in
      1977) and reached a wide audience in the US as well as Europe
      (Myerhoff and Littman 1976).</p>
      <p>In sum, the ongoing debate about representation and the
      construction of our research subjects through text and image has
      had a lasting impact on ethnographic practice. The so-called ‘new
      ethnographies’ took a number of different forms (see Lutkehaus and
      Cool 1999: 118, e.g. Robert Gardner’s
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">Forest of Bliss</hi> (1986); Trinh
      Minh-ha’s <hi rendition="simple:italic">Reassemblage</hi> (1982);
      and the works of Behar (1996), Dalsgård (2013), Stewart (1996) and
      Taussig (2011), to name only a few examples). Simultaneously,
      stories of individual lives have evolved as an anthropological
      genre. Crapanzano’s <hi rendition="simple:italic">Tuhami</hi></p>
      <p>(1980) as well as Shostak’s <hi rendition="simple:italic">Life
      of a !Kung woman</hi> (1981), and Behar’s
      <hi rendition="simple:italic">Translated Women</hi> (1993), are
      amongst the best known examples of a new dialogical engagement
      within the written domain. Taking into consideration that the core
      of my work lies in the life stories of Hamuda Djerbi and Cise
      Ibrahima, I will discuss these contributions in more detail in
      Chapter 3.</p>
      <p>It was with Stewart’s <hi rendition="simple:italic">A Space on
      the Side of the Road</hi> (1996) that I started to discover works
      that combine text, images and/or sound into one research outcome.
      Stewart uses photography and text in a moving way in her portrait
      of the ‘other’ America. By creating short and fragmented images,
      she provides glimpses into people in the places where they carry
      on their everyday encounters. Her attempt to resist ‘the premature
      urge to classify, code, contextualize and name long enough to
      imagine something of the texture and density of spaces of desire
      that proliferate in Othered places’ (1996: 26) has influenced my
      own thinking during research and writing.</p>
      <p>There are many works to write about and it is difficult to
      navigate through all the examples that came to the foreground in
      the aftermath of the writing culture debate; I have here only
      pointed to the works that have stayed imprinted in my memory and
      thus have become influential for my own thoughts. I am convinced
      that a productive collaboration of art and anthropology leads to a
      deeper insight into understanding and representing the
      relationship between people’s lives and the public realm, and can
      move anthropology closer to people. By letting the material shape
      the form, I attempt to counter the imposition of a uniform
      description onto often unruly chaos (Stoller 2016b) and give
      research outcomes a ‘life beyond academy’ (Behar 1999). Working
      with people on the margins of a city that is mostly known for
      lobbying, commissions, international policy meetings and its
      ability to ‘breed terrorism’, ultimately means bringing them out
      of the margins and into the centre of this work.</p>
    
  </div>
  <div type="level2" xml:id="crafting-along">
    <head>CRAFTING ALONG</head>
    
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">08.25 am</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Locking the scooter, freezing
      fingers ‘Bonjour!’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">‘Bonjour!’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Cold cigarette breath</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Big hands, firm shakes, the
      squeaking of the metal door ‘Bonjour ma belle!’ – again</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Up the stairs, signing
      in</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">A little mark above my name
      ‘Coffee? Milk?’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">‘Oui, oui, merci!’ ‘Ça
      va?’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">‘Ça va, et toi?’ one shout - two
      trembling ears. Somewhere laughter, ‘Did you see…’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Down the stairs Iron
      lockers</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Pants off, pants on, a sip of
      coffee 2 more minutes</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Anna enters in a rush
      ‘Salut!’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">‘Salut!’</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">A face that has unlearned to
      smile ‘My boy is sick again!’ she sighs</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">simultaneous gestures, shoulder
      tapping, tool belt on</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">careful instructions planning,
      trimming, cutting marking, joining, assembling sanding,
      creosoting, painting</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">‘A perfect work for such fine
      hands!’ Says Ramzi,</hi></p>
      <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">a chuckle to himself</hi></p>
    
  </div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>